Downloaded @ subs4free.club
It does now seem like
that sometime
in the last couple of days
there's been perhaps
the worst accident
in the short history
of the world's nuclear
power industry.
In Moscow,
Western diplomats have spent the day
trying to get more information
about the accident
with no success.
A zone with a
19-mile radius around Chernobyl
remains a poisoned
no man's land.
Soviet television tonight
accused the western media
of spreading
slanderous inventions
about the Chernobyl accident.
It's now
clear that the Soviet Union
has suffered one of
the worst disasters
in the history of nuclear power.
Massive quantities of radiation
have apparently been
released in an accident
at the Chernobyl Power
Station in the Ukraine.
The Soviet version is this,
one of the atomic reactors
at the Chernobyl
Atomic Power Plant
in the city of Kyiv was damaged
and there is
speculation in Moscow
that people were injured
and may have died.
The Soviets may
have been fairly quick
to acknowledge the accident
because evidence in the form
of mild and nuclear radiation
have already reached
beyond the Soviet borders
to Scandinavia.
There are indications
the accident could have happened
several days ago.
It would take that long
for radiation to
drift to Scandinavia
and to make the
political decision
to announce it.
You can be sure
that the decision
to, to disclose
was made at the
very highest level,
undoubtedly by
Gorbachev himself.
The Soviet press is paying
signally little attention
to the disaster.
Newspapers carry only
the brief official announcement
inconspicuously placed.
People have noticed
the small paragraph
but seemed unaware
of the potential dangers.
People in
the cities, towns, and villages
of the Ukraine
just haven't been told
what dangers they may face.
On the eve of the Seven
Nation Summit in Tokyo
both Mrs. Thatcher
and President Reagan
have urged the Russians to
say more about Chernobyl.
Meeting
with Italy's Premier Craxi,
Mr. Reagan was demanding
answers from the Russians.
Come forward and tell
everybody exactly what happened.
You can hardly call this kind
of an accident an internal affair
when other countries
are threatened
with the fallout of ra...
dangerous radioactivity.
A report in this morning's
Communist party
newspaper "Pravda"
indicates that the fire
at the power station
still may not have been put out
ten days after it started.
The newspaper says
there was an explosion
followed by two
fires at the plant.
The "Pravda" pays
tribute to the firemen whose efforts
it says limited the scale of
the damage considerably.
"Brave bold men" it calls them,
fighting courageously,
hardly able to breathe
for soot and smoke,
their boots sticking
in the asphalt
melted by the high temperatures.
As an
American I'm very privileged
to be able to represent
in the Soviet Union the
concern of Americans.
We have agreed
to a joint Soviet-American
effort in this regard.
Until the accident,
there were 50 nuclear reactors
operating in the Soviet Union
generating 11% of
that nation's electricity.
Most of the larger Soviet plants
differ in design
from US reactors.
The major difference is
most Soviet nuclear
plants do not have
containment buildings,
the thick concrete
dome structures
Americans are used to
seeing built around US reactors.
When the worst American
nuclear accident occurred
at Three Mile Island,
most leaking radiation
was kept inside
the containment building.
If as seems to be the case
there was no containment
around the reactor
as is the general...
Can we be
sure of that? What do you...
I do not, I do not know.
Do you think
there's a containment building?
I don't think that there
is a containment building
because the policy of
Soviet atomic constructors
was that the reactor's
absolutely safe
and so there is no need to
have this kind of precaution
because it indicate
possibility of disaster
which Russian
always con-considered,
uh, absolutely impossible.
So going to be clear about
this, you're, you're going
as far as to say you think it
almost certain or just probable
there was no protective
shield around this reactor
which appears to
have melted down?
No, I think that
there is no protection,
protection shield
around this reactor's
certainly the case,
because the building
as such indicate
that there is no shield.
Walter Patterson, if that is so,
what is the danger to life?
Well, obviously if radioactivity
got as far as Scandinavia,
how long, however
long it took to get there,
a great deal must have
escaped close to the site.
What has been remarkable
is how much the Soviet people
in spite of all the evidence
still seem to be believing
the fairy stories the
government is still telling them.
It could be argued, Martin,
that only the Soviet
Union could have kept a lid
on what might have been
a situation of public panic,
only a totalitarian state
could have got away with it.
I'm not sure they
have got away with it.
Sunday's outbreak of fighting
is only the latest in
four months of violence
in the tiny Caucasian
republic of Georgia.
Spasms of
unrest in the Soviet Union
were felt in the
southern republics
of Azerbaijan and Armenia.
The rebellion
against Communist authority
has now spread
and there's almost certainly
more trouble to come.
The decision to send in troops
was taken by
President Gorbachev.